I'm fascinated by natural selection the
idea that incredible complexity and
environmental adaptation is a
consequence of small random changes it
should be no surprise that I've been a
fan of the primer YouTube channel for
quite a while the channel digs deep into
ideas of evolution by natural selection
and more I'm also a fan of simulations
obviously so when primer released a
video titled simulating natural
selection my programmers fingers got
itchy I like learning by playing I
wanted to get my hands on the controls
and see what other kinds of things I
could learn from these cute unassuming
blob creatures that was a year ago since
then I got in touch with Justin and took
on the task of giving his blob creatures
a new home in a web browser this is the
evolution simulator I tried to keep it
as similar to the original as I could
but since I had to rewrite everything
from scratch there might be a few minor
differences let's go through the laws
governing blob world first in any
generation every blob needs to eat one
piece of food and return to the edge of
the world to survive to the next
generation if a blob gets two pieces of
food then it will reproduce but blobs
have a fixed amount of energy they can
use every day to move around finding
food and the rate that they use up
energy depends on three traits first
trade is sight range blobs will move in
a random way until a piece of food
enters their range vision once a blob
can see food it will move straight
towards it and eat it that is unless
another blob beats them to it
which brings us to the next rate the
speed trait is how fast a blob can move
there's not much more to say than that
you can enable a speed indicator that
makes the faster blobs a brighter red
color as shown here the third trait is
size here's where things get interesting
larger blobs can eat smaller blobs if
they are at least 20% larger and if they
are fast enough to catch them
I should mention one in specific
difference between the primer simulation
and mine and that has to do with how
speed works
I noticed that really tiny blobs could
move lightning-fast because their size
and speed weren't related at all this
looked weird to me a blob the size of an
ant shouldn't be able to keep up with a
default sized blob under normal
circumstances so what I did was I
coupled the speed and size together if a
blob is larger it will be able to move
faster than a smaller blob with the same
speed value think of it like how fast
your limbs can move if you can take the
same number of steps per second as an
ant you will cover more distance just
because of the fact that you're gigantic
compared to the end anyways seeing
farther moving faster and using fellow
blobs as a source of food are certainly
advantages but each of them comes with a
cost
as they say there's no such thing as a
free lunch and these blobs pay in energy
every time a blob moves it loses energy
proportional to its site range plus its
size cubed times its speed squared we
could have chosen any energy cost
relationship we like but Justin chose
this energy cost to resemble the formula
for kinetic energy which makes a lot of
sense when blobs manage to eat two bits
of food and return to the edge of the
board they are able to reproduce this
means the blob is duplicated but each of
the duplicates traits are bumped up or
down by our
random amount for example for any given
blobs offspring there's an equal chance
of it being larger or smaller faster or
slower seeing farther or being condemned
to wander alone in the darkness unaware
of the scrumptious green Ward's waiting
beyond the edge of its nose that is to
say there's nothing built into the
simulation that forces younger blobs to
be better at reproducing than their
parents we don't even know what better
would be exactly but we don't need to
given enough time a large populations
traits will on average evolve towards an
optimum for survival in the current
environment blobs that by chance have
traits closer to the optimum will have a
higher chance of reproducing and their
offspring will have trait values closer
to those successful parents than the
rest of the population you can get an
overview of this adaptation by looking
at the trends page this shows how the
traits of the blob population change
over time the brightest line is the
average value of the trait the region
around the average is the standard
deviation which gives you an idea of how
spread out the values are in the
population the highest and lowest lines
are the maximum and minimum values for
the trait they correspond to the blobs
at the top and bottom of the pack for
example with these parameters when we
look at site range we can see a bunch of
generations where there is a huge spread
in the standard deviation we can switch
back to the worldview look at a
generation around this time and turn on
the site range indicators to see the
street value for every blob some of
these circles are really big and others
are really small there's a lot of
deviation in the site range in this
generation but switching back to the
trends page we can see a bunch of
generations where the standard deviation
in the site range is small
if we look at the blob world around that
time we can see that the sight range
circles are roughly the same size if you
experiment with this a bit you can
notice some really interesting things
about how the blobs evolve for example
we can change how different baby blobs
will be from their parents by changing
the mutation variants in the settings if
we have a mutation variants in the size
trait of around 1 that means the baby
blobs will have a chance of being bigger
or smaller than their parents by a value
of around 1 let's turn up the playback
speed and watch the blobs evolve for a
while notice that the small blobs are
usually the last to find food
that's because being small is much more
energy efficient so smaller blobs can
wander around looking for food for
longer if we focus on one of the large
blobs we can see that all it has time to
do is chase a smaller blob and eat it
before it runs out of energy
and has to return home a smaller blob on
the other hand can wander a very long
time before running out of energy so
there's a selection pressure towards
being smaller because smaller blobs can
spend more time looking for two pieces
of food and if we look at the trend for
the size trait we can see that it
decreases from a value of 10 down to
around 8 in 600 generations so what
happens if we decrease the mutation
variance in the size trait so that baby
blobs are less different than their
parents will the average size decrease
slower than before because they are
mutating their size less
turns out to be the opposite in 600
generations the size decreases to seven
instead of nine so if the blobs are
mutating less why does their average
size evolve faster if we compare the two
worlds we can see why this could be the
case in the first world there were blobs
of many different sizes competition was
fierce and if a blob happened to be
smaller than the average there was a
larger chance that it was small enough
to be eaten by a bigger blob but in this
new world where the variation in size
between blobs is small most blobs are
roughly the same size so there's almost
no chance of being next to another blob
that is big enough to pose a threat in
other words there's no cost and being
slightly smaller so the average will
decrease at a steady rate this is a good
thing to keep in mind just because
there's a huge amount of mutation
doesn't mean evolution happens faster
the speed of evolution depends on the
Selective pressures in the environment
there's something else I noticed when
playing around with this that I found
really amazing it has to do with the age
of the blobs the age is how many
generations a blob has existed so far a
newly born blob for example will have an
age of zero and if it survives to the
next generation it will have an age of
one the weird thing is this
the average age of the blobs in a
generation grows to around two and then
levels off no matter how I changed the
settings it does this every time it
looks like there must be some
fundamental rule here to be discovered
so why does this happen I actually think
this explanation deserves its own video
so I'll save it for another time until
then you're welcome to try to figure it
out for yourself and I'd love to hear in
the comments what kinds of behaviors and
trends you notice while playing around
with this as usual thanks so much to
those of you supporting me on patreon
and I should mention that there's
another way to support me that would
actually help me out even more I've
enabled github sponsors on my projects
if you have a github account you can go
over to my profile or a minute labs
github repository and click the sponsor
button if you sponsor bean by any amount
I get every penny of that money not only
that but github will match every
donation I get through github sponsors
which effectively doubles all donations
and no additional cost to you so I hope
you consider doing that if you do let me
know and I can add you to the list of
minute labs beta-testers if you'd like
soon enough I'll be releasing
enhancements to the evolution simulator
to allow you to change how the blobs
behave even more so I'll see you again
sooner than usual with something new
[Music]